2001年 一位美国海军F-18战斗机飞行员从航空母舰上起飞
In 2001, the pilot of an F-18 taking off from a US Navy aircraft carrier
但他做出了一个让人匪夷所思的举动
did something that very few people would see coming.
在一个乌云密布的漆黑夜晚
Immediately after being catapulted during a dark night with low clouds,
飞行员在弹射起飞后莫名开始推杆 导致飞机俯冲坠入海中
the pilot mysteriously pushed the nose of the aircraft down and descended into the ocean.
为了弄清原因 我们今天来聊聊这个——
And to figure out why, today we're going to talk about this.
代尔夫特理工大学的SIMONA研究模拟机
The Delft University of Technology's SIMONA research simulator.
整台机器只有一个用处
This entire machine has one purpose,
那就是欺骗人的大脑 让它感觉你在驾驶真正的飞机
and that is to trick your brain into feeling like it's flying a real aircraft.
该模拟机位于荷兰代尔夫特市
Located in the city of Delft in the Netherlands,
使用三台投影仪在环幕上生成图像
the simulator uses three projectors to generate an image on this dome,
向飞行员展示驾驶舱内看到的虚拟景象
showing the pilots a virtual view from the cockpit.
整个驾驶舱由六个液压推杆支撑
The entire cabin is supported by six hydraulic actuators,
让模拟机有六个自由度的运动
which are used to move the simulator in all six dimensions,
三个方向的平移
three translations,
和三个方向的旋转
and three rotations.
但模拟机的动作是如何与飞机的实际动作相对应的?
But how did the simulators movements correspond to the actual movements of the aircraft?
其中的关键是 人们在乘坐飞机时会有什么样的感觉?
And more importantly, what kinds of sensations do people even feel when they're flying in a plane?
因为我们即将了解到
Because as we're about to find out,
模拟机本质上并不是要与飞机的运动本身相匹配
the goal of the simulator is actually not to match the aircraft's movements per se.
举例来说 飞行员在向前水平飞行的时候
For example, it's entirely possible for the pilot to be flying straight and level,
从外面看模拟机 它的姿态完全可能是在抬头或低头
but looking at the simulator from the outside, you might see the platform pitching up or down,
这点可能与一般人预想的不同
which is not what you'd initially expect.
不过 在我们探讨这些看似矛盾的问题之前
But before we get into these seeming paradoxes,
可以先聊聊研究人员为什么要在这些问题上花费如此多的时间和精力
it's worth talking about why researchers spend so much time and effort on these things in the first place.
因为大学航空航天工程系的人员几乎每天都在使用SIMONA
Since almost every day SIMONA is being used by the TUDelft faculty of Aerospace Engineering
研究飞行员如何控制飞机并与之互动
to learn about how pilots control and interact with aircraft.
我们的研究领域之一是运动模拟
One of the areas of our research focuses on motion cueing,
即研究如何通过操纵飞行员的感官 以最佳方式欺骗他们的感知
which is about figuring out how to optimally fool the perceptions of pilots by manipulating their senses.
为此 我们不妨考虑一下人类感官的输入和输出
For this, it's useful to think about humans having inputs and outputs.
例如在研究过程中 飞行员的行为通常是通过黑盒法来模拟的
For example, during research, pilot behaviour is often modelled with something called the black box method.
该方法中 我们将人类飞行员想象成某种未知的算法
This is where we imagined the human operator to be some unknown algorithm
算法会从环境中获取一系列输入
that takes a set of inputs from the environments.
比如仪表 目视跑道 甚至声音
Things like instruments, the view of the runway, and even sounds, for example.
如果我们把人类想象成一种算法
If we imagine humans as an algorithm,
那么我们最重要的输入之一来自我们的前庭系统或内耳
then one of our most important inputs comes from our vestibular system, or inner ear,
它可以感知角加速度等信息
which can sense things like angular acceleration.
众所周知 内耳不仅对我们的平衡感起着重要作用
Our inner ear is not only known to play a significant role in our sense of balance,
还能极大地影响飞行员的行为
but can also drastically affect pilots behavior
在某些情况下甚至会导致迷向
and can even cause disorientation in certain situations.
奇怪的是 我们人类算法的另一个重要感官输入是座椅
Another important input to our human algorithm is, weirdly enough, your seat,
或者更具体地说 你的身体和支撑你的椅子之间的作用力
or more specifically, the forces between your body and the chair that supporting you.
我们先从俯仰 滚转和偏航开始
Let's start with the rotation in pitch roll and yaw.
作为首次尝试 我们先让模拟机平台与飞机的姿态一致
As a first try, let's just move the platform to match the orientation of the aircraft.
比如如果你想左转
So for example, if you're making a turn to the left,
那模拟机平台就跟着飞机向左倾斜
let's just try rotating the platform to match the roll angle of the plane.
表面看上去符合逻辑 但很快你就会发现这种方法存在的问题
Although this seems logical, rather quickly, you'd find that this method has some problems.
如果大家记得坐飞机转弯时
If you've ever been in a normal turn in a real aircraft,
虽然有点反直觉 但大家可能会注意到 身体并不会感受到倾斜
you may have noticed that, paradoxically, it never really feels like you're being tilted at an angle,
哪怕此时飞机的滚转坡度已经达到了30度
even if the aircraft is being rolled by as much as 30 degrees.
这就好比以一定速度骑摩托车时 车需要向弯心倾斜一样
This is similar to how you need to lean your bike towards the inside of the turn, when you're cycling at a certain speed.
车速越快 或者弯道越急 为了保持平衡 滚转角度越大
The faster the bike travels, or the tighter the turn, the more roll you'll need to stay balanced,
对飞机来说也是一样道理
which is also the case in an aircraft.
但回到我们的模拟机上来
But if we look at our simulator,
你会发现这并不适用 因为平台实际上并不能到处乱跑
you'll notice that this doesn't apply since the platform isn't actually traveling anywhere.
因此 如果我们倾斜模拟机 使其与飞机的滚转坡度相匹配
As a result, if we move the simulator to match the roll angle of the plane,
就好比倾斜一辆完全静止的自行车
it would be like tilting a bike that standing still.
在重力的作用下 自行车自然会倒下
Due to gravity, the bike would of course fall over.
而在我们的模拟机中
And in our simulator,
这意味着飞行员会感受到模拟机带坡度时会有一种不真实的侧向力
this means that people will feel an unrealistic side force as a consequence of the simulators roll.
现在我们已经了解到 如果我们以恒定的滚转坡度进行转弯
So now we've established that if we're in a coordinated turn with a constant roll angle,
模拟器应该保持水平才对 很好
then the simulator must stay level, which is great.
那开始转弯和结束转弯怎么办?
But what about when we enter and exit a turn?
如果滚转角度随时间变化
If the roll angle is changing over time,
那么这个坡度的变化速度就称为滚转率
then the rate at which this angle changes is called the roll rate.
这个概念非常重要 因为人类的内耳能够感知到滚转率的变化
This is important to know because your inner ear can sense when the roll rate itself changes.
因此 我们确实需要模拟机跟着滚转
So as it turns out, we do actually need the simulator to roll.
但不能滚太多 不能倾斜太久
But we can't do this too much or for too long,
否则 飞行员就会开始感受到不真实的重力侧向分力
because otherwise the pilots will start to feel unrealistic side forces due to gravity.
为了解决这个问题 工程师们使用了"洗出滤波"算法
To solve this problem, engineers use an algorithm called a washout filter,
该算法将飞机的姿态变化与模拟机平台的角度联系起来
which links that dynamics of the aircraft to the roll angle of the simulator platform.
为了直观展现
To see this filter in action,
画面左侧是飞行员看到的飞行景象
on the left hand side of the screen, you can see the pilot's view of the aircraft,
右侧是飞机姿态变化经洗出滤波算法处理后作用在模拟机上的结果
and on the right hand side you can see the effect of the washout filter
and how it's controlling the tilt of the platform based on the movements of the aircraft.
注意滚转率开始
Notice how the roll rate starts,
与停止的瞬间
and then stops again.
每当滚转率发生变化
Every time the roll rate changes,
模拟机平台就会迅速向变化的方向倾斜
the platform quickly tilts in the direction of that change.
如果我把下面的曲线加上
And if I add the graphs down below,
大家可以非常清楚看到左侧滚动率的变化
you can see very clearly how changes in roll rates on the left
是如何带动右侧平台滚动的
are activating the roll angle of the platform on the right.
这种动态变化正是触发人类前庭系统的原因
These dynamics are exactly what's going to trigger your vestibular system.
而洗出滤波真正巧妙的地方
But the really clever parts of the washout filter
就在于一旦滚动率下降
lies in the fact that as soon as the roll rates come down,
平台就会回中 或零坡度状态
then the platform will always tend to move back to neutral or zero roll.
这就是所谓的洗出信号
This is called washing out the signal,
它确保我们不会让平台倾斜太久
and it makes sure that we never tilt the platform for too long.
大家可能已经猜到 这正是我们苦苦寻找的消除侧向力的方法
And as you might have guessed, it's also exactly what we need
to stop the side forces that we've been struggling with.
在俯仰轴和偏航轴上也应用上洗出滤波后
By also applying washout filters to the pitch and yaw axis,
我们算是解决了飞机的旋转运动
we've now got a solution for the aircraft's rotational movement.
但旋转并不是模拟机平台能够处理的唯一运动类型
But rotations aren't the only type of movement that the platform is capable of dealing with,
我们尚未讨论的是飞行员因加速度和重力而感受到的力
something we haven't yet talked about are the forces that the pilot feels due to acceleration and gravity.
为此 我们需要讨论"比力"的概念
And for this, we need to talk about a concept called specific force.
举个简单的例子 当飞机大仰角匀速爬升的时候 飞行员感受如何?
An easy example is to consider what the pilot would feel
when the aircraft is in a climb with a high pitch angle at a constant speed.
由于仰角的存在
Because of the pitch angle,
重力的分力会指向机尾
a portion of gravity will be pulling backwards relative to the plane.
因此 飞行员会感受到座椅靠背对身体向前的支撑力
In turn, the pilot will feel the forward reaction force of their seat as it supports their body.
要让飞行员在模拟机中感受到这种力
To get the pilot to feel this force in the simulator,
只需让模拟机平台抬头就行
we can simply pitch the platform up,
这样也会产生与真实飞机相同的反作用力
which will also cause a forward reaction force in the same way that the real plane does.
这个简单的例子表明 人类似乎可以感知重力的分力
This simple example seems to suggest that humans can sense components of gravity,
或者说至少在一些情况下如此
or at least under certain circumstances.
尽管这种方法的方向是对的 但我们还没有考虑到全部情况
And although this approach is definitely heading in the right direction, we haven't yet covered the full picture.
如果我们水平飞行 看看会发生什么
Let's take a look at what happens if we're flying straight and level.
这次 飞机是在加速 即加速度为定值
But this time with increasing speed, which is to say, a certain amount of acceleration.
首先注意到 在整个飞行过程中 重力将始终垂直向下
First of all, notice how throughout the maneuver gravity will be pointing straight down,
即不会贡献任何水平方向分力
which means that it won't contribute to any horizontal forces.
在加速过程中 你自己会感觉来自座椅的"推背感"
During the acceleration, you'll feel as if you're being pushed into your chair,
这点在起飞时尤其明显
which is especially noticeable during takeoff.
但请注意 此时的感受 是椅子真的在向前推你 在给你的身体加速
But note that what you're actually feeling is the chair pushing you forward
as it accelerates the mass of your body,
由于惯性 身体的质量正试图抵抗这种运动
which is trying to resist this movement due to inertia.
因此 为了让飞行员体验到这种力
So to get the pilot to experience this force,
模拟机需要像刚刚重力分力情况中 以完全相同的方式倾斜
we would have to tilt the simulator in exactly the same way as we did in the gravity situation.
但请记住 即使平台是向上抬头的
But keep in mind that even though the platform is pitching up,
内部环幕上的视觉信息给飞行员的感觉仍然是水平直线飞行
the visual information on the inside dome
gives pilots the feeling that they're flying straight and level.
毕竟这是飞行员唯一能看到的信息
Since this is the only visual information that they have.
这会给飞行员一种错觉 即飞机正在直线加速飞行
This creates the illusion that the aircraft is accelerating straight ahead,
飞行员会相信这样的错觉
which to the pilots is not only believable,
而且几乎无法抵抗这样的感觉
but almost impossible to resist,
因为他们所有的感官收到的错觉信息是一致的
since all of their sensory organs are giving them a consistent illusion.
即使我们认为重力的分力 与水平加速是两种不同的现象
So even if we choose to think about gravity and acceleration as two separate phenomena,
但重要的是 没有我们眼睛看到的信息作为补充
it's crucial to realize that without the context provided by your eyes,
这两者在靠背上的感觉就是相同的
gravity and acceleration are experienced as the same sensation.
这也解释了为什么我们在两种情况下都以完全相同的方式倾斜模拟机
That's also explains why we tilt the simulator in exactly the same way in both cases.
对运动系统的一个常见误解是 人类可以区分重力和加速度
A common misunderstanding about motion systems is that humans can feel either gravity or acceleration.
现实中 这并不完全正确
In reality, this isn't entirely true,
因为即使你的大脑可能会将座椅的力量理解为加速度或重力
because even though your brain may interpret the force of your seat as acceleration or gravity,
飞行员唯一能真正感受到的仍然只有座椅本身的力
the only thing that pilots can truly feel is the force of the chair itself.
这种反作用力就是所谓的比力
This reaction force is what is meant by the term specific force.
计算比力的公式其实非常简单
The formula to calculate specific force is actually pretty simple,
同时也为我们提供了一种理解问题的全新视角
and also opens up a whole new way of looking at the problem.
如你所见 该公式表示 人会感受到重力与加速度的共同作用
As you'd expect, the equation suggests that people will feel a combination of acceleration and gravity,
在空间迷向的事件中
and in the event of spatial disorientation,
人类大脑通常就是混淆了这两个部分
it's exactly these two terms that a brain can accidentally mix up.
而这个等式的左侧表示 我们还可以计算出比力
But the left hand side of this equation says that we can also calculate specific force
把除重力外 所有作用在飞机上的力的总和
by summing all the forces acting upon the aircraft except weight,
除以飞机的质量
and then dividing by the mass of the aircraft.
举个例子
To demonstrate how this works,
观察在推力等于阻力的减速爬升过程中会发生什么
let's take a look at what happens in a decelerating climb in which thrust equals drag.
我们将水平方向上除重量以外的所有力相加时
When we take the sum of all forces along the horizontal direction except weight,
发现阻力会抵消推力
then drag will cancel out thrust.
因此 尽管由于重力的作用 会有一个分力将飞机向后拉
So even though there will be a net force pulling the aircraft backwards due to gravity,
这个等式却告诉我们 飞机内的人是感觉不到飞机在减速的
this equation is telling us that the people inside the plane won't be able to feel it.
仔细想想 这完全说得通
And if you think about it, this makes complete sense
因为推动你前进的重力分量 被向后拉你的减速力抵消
since the gravity component that would be pushing you forward
is being canceled by the deceleration, which is pulling you backwards.
就好像你可以在U型池中玩滑板
This is similar to how you can skate up a half pipe,
保持平衡的同时 重力还不会让你摔落滑板
but stay completely balanced on the skateboard without gravity pulling you off of it.
最后 如果你是一名工程师 想要计算飞行员感受到的力
Finally, if you're an engineer who's trying to calculate the forces that the pilots are feeling,
计算空气动力和推力的总和 要比计算加速度和重力分量容易得多
it's way easier to simply sum the aerodynamic and thrust forces
than to calculate accelerations and gravity components.
当然 这两种方法得出的结果是一样的
Even though both methods will, of course lead to the same result.
为了让模拟机更加逼真 我们还可以采用最后一个技巧
To make the simulator even more realistic, there's one final trick that we can implement.
在一个力突然爆发的瞬间
During the first few moments of a particularly quick force,
比如飞行员突然把油门推到底
let's say if the pilot slams the throttles,
整个平台可以一边向前平移一边抬头
the entire platform will move forward as it pitches up.
这样做是有原因的
And there is a very good reason for this.
当模拟机平台利用俯仰创造比力的时候
When the platform pitches to induce specific force,
模拟机平台的旋转速度是有限制的
there is a limit to how fast we can rotate the simulator,
因为如果我们抬头太快
since if we pitched too quickly,
飞行员的内耳会产生错误的旋转提示
this would result in false rotational cues coming from the pilot's inner ear.
当飞机开始加速时
As the aircraft initially accelerates,
我们可以利用模拟器的平移轴 让您在座位上有推背感
we can use the surge axis of the simulator to give the feeling of being pushed in your seats.
然后 当平台开始抬头旋转时
Then, as the platform starts to rotate,
我们可以缓解并洗出平移的分量 让重力接管这部分感知
we can ease and wash out the surge to let gravity take over
并产生我们所需的持续的比力
and produce the long term specific force that we need.
其他方向也可以应用同样的洗出滤波
We can also apply the same to filters in the other direction as well.
高频运动可以通过平台的平移来消除
High frequency movements are washed out by translating the platform,
而较慢的低频力则通过模拟机的滚动来实现
whereas slower low frequency forces are taken care of by rolling the simulator.
说到这里 你可能会想
At this point you might be thinking,
好 如果重力和加速度的体验是相同的
well, if gravity and acceleration are experienced in exactly the same way,
对人类来说体感也是完全一样的
and are therefore in some sense the same,
那我们的大脑又怎么知道哪边向上呢?
how can our brains know literally which way is up?
毕竟人们在日常生活中又不会经常因为平衡感知错乱而摔得四脚朝天
I mean, it's not as if people are constantly falling over in daily life
because their sense of balance is all confused.
这是因为我们对世界的方位感知很大一部分来自视觉
This is because a large part of our sense of orientation in the world
comes from our eyes and our visual field.
这也是我们能用模拟机很好地欺骗飞行员的原因
This is also the reason that we can do such an amazing job at tricking people in our flight simulators,
因为事实上 模拟机平台的移动并不必须与飞机的姿态完全一致
because the fact that the movement of the platform
does not necessarily need to correspond with the orientation of the aircraft,
这正是理解和设计全动模拟机运动系统的关键所在
is the key to understanding and designing motion systems.
这也让我们回过头来审视F-18坠毁的原因
This also brings us full circle to what caused the F-18 to crash.
由于当时天色阴暗 飞行员没有足够多的目视参考
Because it was dark and cloudy, the pilot didn't have the same amount of visual cues
无法有效将重力与弹射的加速度区分开来
which would otherwise allow him to disentangle gravity from acceleration.
因此 弹射时的加速度被误认为是重力
As a result, the acceleration of the launch got misinterpreted as gravity,
也就是说 飞行员感觉自己正在急速爬升
meaning that he felt as if he was in a steep climb.
为了减少他错觉中的爬升
In an effort to reduce the climb that he thought was happening,
他将操纵杆向前一推 硬生生扎进了海里
he pushed the stick forward and the aircraft descended into the ocean.
如果您有兴趣在代尔夫特理工大学学习 或与这所世界领先的机构合作
If you're interested in studying at TU Delft or working with this world leading institution,
欢迎前往视频原地址 并考虑加入我们
you should really consider joining us by checking the description.
在此 非常感谢代尔夫特大学航空航天工程学院 控制与仿真部的
Olaf Stroosma、René van Paassen和Max Mulder
On that notes, huge thanks to Olaf Stroosma, René van Paassen, and Max Mulder
在此 非常感谢代尔夫特大学航空航天工程学院 控制与仿真部的
Olaf Stroosma、René van Paassen和Max Mulder
from the Control and Simulation section at the Faculty of Aerospace Engineering.
非常感谢大家的观看 我们下次再见
Thank you very much for watching and I hope to see you again soon.